Today's דף *daf* is פ"ו *Peh Vav*, and we pick up in
the middle of פ"ה עמוד ב' bet *Peh Hey Amud Bet* or
like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* top of פ"ה עמוד ב' *Peh Hey
Amud Bet*, so we got a little ground to cover. And we
just read the משנה Mishna *mishna* that said the key line of
a גט Get *get* was הרי את מותרת לכל אדם Harei At
Muteret Lechol Adam. *harei at muteret le-chol adam*. So and then רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* said that the גט get *get* has
to be more spelled out, it should say ודן *v'den* should be
to you from me a bill of divorce and a writ of
of release etc. etc. So not only does it have more words,
but it also is self-referential
and says that it just says that this itself is functioning as
that instrument of divorce. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, about four lines from the top on פ"ה עמוד ב' *Peh
Hey Amud Bet*. פשיטא *Peshita*, אמר ליה לאשתו *amar lei l'ishto* הרי
את בת חורין *harei at bat chorin*, if a man says to
his wife, you are a free woman,
לא lo, אמר כלום *lo amar klum*, that's meaningless because even though
she's like free from him but the meaning of בת חורין *bat
chorin* means you're not a slave, and that's not a language of
divorce. אמר ליה לשפחתו *amar lei l'shifchato*, if he says to his
female slave הרי את מותרת לכל אדם harei at muteret le-chol adam.
*harei at muteret le-chol adam*, you are permissible to marry any man,
לא אמר כלום *lo amar klum*, that's also not relevant because that's
not about her status of being a slave or free woman. אמר
ליה לאשה *amar lei l'isha*, now but what if he says to
his wife הרי את לעצמך *harei at le-atzmech*, you are under your
own control. Now that's a language that can work for freeing a
slave, but it also is general enough that it could be relevant
for the idea of being no longer under your husband's control and
maybe means a divorce as well. מהו *mahu*, what do we say?
לגמרי קאמר לה *legamrei ka'amar lah*, does it mean fully and therefore
it relates to marriage as well and it's a language of divorce,
או למלאכה קאמר לה *o lemelacha ka'amar lah*, or does it mean
that you know I no longer own your labor which again makes
it relevant to freeing a slave but does not make it relevant
to divorcing a wife. Again, this is if this is what's written
in the גט get *get*, this is the key line of the
גט get? *get* instead of הרי את מותרת לכל אדם harei at
muteres l'chol adam. *harei at muteret le-chol adam*. אמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי *amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi*, so רבינא *Ravina* said to רב
Rav אשי *Rav Ashi*, תא שמע ta shma, *ta shma*, come and
hear, דתנן *d'tnan*, as we've learned in the משנה Mishna. *mishna*, גופה
של גט get שחרור *gufa shel get shichrur*, the essence of a
writ of freedom is הרי את בת חורין *harei at bat chorin*,
behold you are a free person, הרי את לעצמך *harei at le-atzmech*,
or you are, this is our משנה Mishnah. *mishna*, you are under
your own control. So that works for freeing a slave. So it
says ומה עבדא דקני ליה גופיה *uma avda dekani lei gufei*, so
by a slave, because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually didn't, of the
two possibilities, didn't say it meant freeing a slave, it said either
it meant לגמרי *legamrei* and would work for divorce, or it means
I am like releasing you from my right of your labor, okay,
but that also that's not a full sense of ownership. But the
response is is that if you look in the משנה Mishnah. *mishna*,
if it works for a real slave, then it's really not just
releasing somebody from your rights to their labor, it's a complete withdrawal
of your control, a full separation. ומה *uma*, so he says ומה
עבדא דקני ליה גופיה *uma avda dekani lei gufei*, a slave that
you actually own the body of the slave, כי ki אמר ליה
הרי את לעצמך *ki amar lei harei at le-atzmech*, if you say
this word you are to yourself, קני גופיה *kani gufei*, so the
slave now owns his or she owns him or herself, so really
refers to a full removal of control, it's not just waiving some
rights to the labor. אשה דלא קני ליה גופיה *isha d'lo kani
lei gufei*, so by a woman that his control, his ownership is
not as full as that of a slave, לא כל שכן *lo
kol sheken*, how much more so that הרי את לעצמך *harei at
le-atzmech* means a withdrawal of all control, of all ownership. So basically
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is you know because הרי את
לעצמך *harei at le-atzmech* does not have as much of an implication
of change of status as הרי את מותרת לכל אדם *harei at
muteret le-chol adam* or הרי את בת חורין *harei at bat chorin*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says look if it works by a
slave, you see that it can mean, you know not just some
waiving of rights, but it does mean fundamentally freeing somebody or a
full removal of control, and if that can work by a slave,
it can work by a language for a woman. So the only
reason בת חורין *bat chorin* does not work is because בת חורין
*bat chorin* has the very specific meaning of being a free person
as contrasted to being a slave. But if you have something that
does not have that very specific meaning of slave versus free person,
and more has a general sense of a full removal of any
sense of ownership and control, so that's a generic enough language that
can work both for a writ of freedom, a writ of manumission
for a slave, and a writ of divorce, because as long as
it's not specific, doesn't have the specific meaning of slave versus free
person, if it just means I'm completely removing any control and any
ownership I have over you, then that can work for both. Okay
so אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi*, so
רבינא *Ravina* said to רב Rav אשי *Rav Ashi*, אמר ליה לעבדיה
*amar lei l'avdei*, somebody said to his slave, אין לי עסק בך
Ein Lei Eisek Becha *ein li esek bach*, מהו *mahu*, I have
I will have no dealings with you, what's the story? Because that
doesn't sound like you're changing the person's status or giving the person
back their own ownership of their own body, it just more sounds
again like I'm a waiving of rights, but it does not really
sound as profound as a full severing of ownership.
So he says what's the story? אמר ליה רב חנן לרב אשי
*amar lei Rav Chanan l'Rav Ashi*, ואמרי ליה רב חנין מחוזנא לרב
אשי *v'amri lei Rav Chanin Mechuza l'Rav Ashi*, so one of these
רב חנן *Rav Chanan* says to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, תא שמע
דתניא *ta shma d'tania*, come and hear that we learned in a
ברייתא *braita*, המוכר עבדו לעובד כוכבים *hamocher avdo l'oveid kochavim*, somebody sells
his slave to a non-Jew, יצא לחירות *yatza l'cherut*. redeem the slave
and the slave goes free. וצריך גט get שחרור מרבו ראשון
but even so, the first master even if he redeems him from
the non-Jew has to still write him a writ of manumission. ואמר
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל V'Amar Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel במה דברים אמורים
Bamei Devarim Amurim when do you need a new sort of writ
of manumission? שלא כתב עליו אונו Shelo Kasav Alav Ono you did
not write the document already. אבל כתב עליו אונו Aval Kasav Alav
Ono if you had already written a document when you sold him
to the non-Jew, זהו שחרורו Zehu Shichruro that serves as the writ
of freedom. מאי אונו Mai Ono what would what's that document? אמר
רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshes דכתב ליה DeChasiv Lei he writes for
him, לכשתברח ממנו LichsheSivrach Mimenu I am selling you to this non-Jew,
but if you ever manage to run away from him, אין לי
עסק בך Ein Lei Eisek Becha I waive my rights to you.
So the point here is that אין לי עסק בך Ein Lei
Eisek Becha functions as a language of a שטר שחרור. Shtar Shichrur.
And that really is a חידוש, Chidush, because אין ein לי li
עסק בך means I will have nothing to do with you, okay?
But that doesn't mean that you no longer own me, meaning it
that might sort of say that you're withdrawing your rights, but there's
still a different thing that you are giving me back ownership of
my own body, a change of status and so on. So but
we find out that that actually does work by a slave. And
then of course the reasonable question would be is, okay, then does
it work by a bill of divorce? Because the גמרא Gemara seems
to say that a language that works by a slave would work
by a bill of divorce, it would be a complete removal of
control, as long as it didn't have the specific meaning of slave
versus free person. So maybe the answer presumably is yes. Okay, so
that's the question of what would work for the key line, for
the punchline. But now we get to the debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma where רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says you have to be much more explicit. You have to
say, this should serve as an instrument of divorce. ודין דיהוי ליכי
מינאי V'Dein DeYihavi Lichi Minai this should be to you from me,
ספר תירוכין ואגרת שבוקין Sefer Teiruchin V'Igeret Shivukin a book of divorce
and a writ of release, etc. Now by the way, if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, you know what, we'll get
to רש"י Rashi in a minute, רש"י's Rashi going to give you
the whole standard נוסח הגט. Nusach HaGet. I read it to you
from the רי"ף Rif a while ago. That's true. Now I'll read
it to you in רש"י, Rashi, yeah.
Yeah, for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda isn't the punchline just the last
phrase?
Oh, and that you can go marry whoever you want? Yeah, it
could be. I mean, that seems just to be more a Aramaic
expression or spelling out of הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. But the
גמרא Gemara, understands that the bigger חידוש Chidush of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is the first beginning of the line, ודין, V'Dein, this is
the writ of... I'm not just making a declaration, this is not
just a document to prove you're divorced, it actually is the instrument
of divorce. That's at least how the גמרא Gemara understands it. He
says a whole big thing, but what's his primary... what was primarily
missing in the earlier statement that he felt he had to supplement?
So the גמרא's Gemara going to say it's fundamentally the ודין, V'Dein,
the self-referential line. במאי קמיפלגי B'Mai Kamifligi what's the debate? רבנן סברי
ידים שאינן מוכיחות הויין ידים Rabbanan Savri Yadayim SheEinan Mochichos Haviyan Yadayim
even though it's a hand, meaning that's not evident, it indicates something,
but it's not explicit. So implicitly is that this is the writ
of divorce itself, this is the instrument of divorce, but it's not
a hundred percent, it didn't say it black and white. And even
if it didn't say it black and white, if it was clearly
the meaning, that would be a ידים מוכיחות, Yadayim Mochichos, but it's
not clearly the meaning. So they said that doesn't matter, it's still,
you know, mostly that's understood that this is itself the instrument, and
that works. Now, meaning you could have said that the debate is
not, are you looking for something, Jenna?
I was looking to open the new bag.
Any scissors? Oh, probably in my top drawer there.
It's okay. Well, one of those top drawers. Thank you very much,
Jenna, I appreciate that. No, you're not finding it? The middle one?
Okay.
Here.
It's alright,
told you...
All there. Got it.
Okay, leave it. Alright, anyway, so thank you. So you could have
said that they're debating what the standards are, right? You could have
said that the rabbis don't need the גט get. to be self-referential.
Why... since when do you need a document to describe itself as
the instrument that it's doing? Like if you talk about what's a
standard שטר מכירה, Shtar Mechira, you know what a standard שטר מכירה
Shtar Mechira is? שדי מכורה לך Sadi Mechura Lach and you hand
the guy the שטר. Shtar. What's a standard שטר קידושין? Shtar Kiddushin?
הרי את מקודשת לי Harei At Mekudeshet Li written on the line
and you hand it. Those documents don't have to be self-referential
and make it clear that they are the instrument. So more simply
you would have said that the rabbis don't even require that, since
when does a document have to make it explicit that it itself
is the instrument? But that's not how the גמרא's Gemara framing the
debate. The גמרא Gemara is saying is that both sides require that
the document be clear that it is the actual instrument, but the
rabbis say, or that it has to sort of, you know,
communicate that, but the rabbis say it does not have to do
it explicitly. It can even be implicitly. ידים שאינן מוכיחות הויין ידים.
Yadayim SheEinan Mochichos Haviyan Yadayim. As long as it's understood and it's
not a hundred percent, but it's pretty clear that's enough that it's
referring to itself as the instrument of divorce. ידים שאינן מוכיחות הויין
ידים Yadayim SheEinan Mochichos Haviyan Yadayim ואף על גב דלא כתב ליה
ודין V'Af Al Gav DeLo Kasav Lei V'Dein even though you did
not write and this. this shall be the instrument of divorce. מוכח
מילתא דבהאי גיטא קמגרש לה, Mochiach milta de-be-hai gitta kama-ga-resh-la, it's clear
that this is the instrument. So again for whatever reason we're assuming
by גט get, which we tend not to assume by other documents
that serve as instruments, that they have to be clear that they
are the instrument, that the גט get. has to be clear that
it is the instrument. And the rabbis say it's clear enough, it
doesn't have to be stated explicitly. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda סבר savar
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is of the opinion, ידיים
שאין מוכיחות לאו הויין ידיים. Yadaim she-ein mochichot lav havyan yadaim. No,
if it's not explicit or it's not absolutely clear then it does
not- it's not like it's made that statement. וטעמא דכתב לה ודין,
Ve-tama de-katav la ve-den, specifically for גט? get, Yeah,
and you have to write ודין, ve-den, you have to be explicit
that this is the instrument. דמוכחא מילתא דבהאי גיטא קמגרש לה, De-mochicha
milta de-be-hai gitta kama-ga-resh-la, that makes it clear that this גט get.
is the instrument through which she's being divorced. אבל לא כתב לה
ודין, Aval lo katav la ve-den, but if it did not say
ודין, ve-den, אמרי, amri, then you could say בדיבורא גירשה, be-dibura girsha,
he's divorcing her just verbally, ושטרא ראיה בעלמא, ve-sh-tara re-aya be-alma, and
this is just serving as some evidence to the fact. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, is saying two things. Number one is it has
to be clear that this is the instrument of divorce and number
two is it will not be able to be clear about that
unless you say it explicitly. Okay, both those are a חידוש, chiddush,
but the first one in my mind is even the bigger חידוש.
chiddush.
You can think of it as a verbal divorce?
No, but that's exactly the point. He says that the גט get.
has to make it clear that it's not a שטרא ראיה, sh-tara
re-aya, that it's- the שטרא sh-tara is actually the instrument. Now why
all of a sudden does a שטרא sh-tara have to make it
clear that it itself is the instrument? I don't know, but that's
what he's saying and therefore you have to say it explicitly and
you have to say ודין. ve-den. Now we're going to talk about
the exact נוסח nusach of the גט. get אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
האי מאן דכתב גיטא, hai man de-katav gitta, from a man writes
a גט, get לא ליכתוב ודין lo lichtov ve-den with a י,
yod, דמשמע ודין de-mash-ma ve-din
because you could read it as it's- it's the law, it's that
I should give you this גט. get But he's not required to
give a גט, get. so that's actually not what he's trying to
say and it's not even accurate. אלא ודן, Ela ve-den, you write
it without the י. yod. ולא ליכתוב איגרת Ve-lo lichtov igeret with
a י, yod, דמשמע איגרת, de-mash-ma igeret, okay,
because it means an איגרא igra and an איגרא igra is a
roof. Okay, so writing it איגרת igeret with a י yod could
mean a roof. This should be to me a- to you a
roof of divorce. אלא אגרת Ela ageret without a י. yod. Okay,
ולא ליכתוב למהך ve-lo lichtov le-me-hach to go to marry any man
you want, דמשמע לי מהך de-mash-ma li me-hach to me from this.
You know, not that you should go and marry, but like to
me you should be a- you know, you should be my wife
in this regard or something of that nature. To be my wife
in regard that you can go marry anybody but you're still divorced?
No, I don't know, that you can go marry any man you
want. But anyway, somehow the word לי li is a sense of
like you're mine still. Okay, אלא, ela, so you should write- so
you should write למהך le-me-hach without the י, yod, which means to
go. Okay,
where were we?
דמשמע לי מהך ולא ליכתוב למהך. de-mash-ma li me-hach ve-lo lichtov le-me-hach.
I think you skipped that part.
Did I? No, that's the next line. Isn't it? Oh you're right,
I skipped this next line. ולא ליכתוב Ve-lo lichtov -- no, no
I didn't, that's one after that yet. Okay, למהך. le-me-hach. So רש"י
Rashi says למהך le-me-hach means
לי תהא מספר זה ואילך li te-hei mi-se-fer zeh va-e-lech to me
it should be from this time onward, I don't know, anyway. Okay,
but לי to me מהך me-hach from this you should go and
blah blah blah, which I don't know, somehow it's not the same
as meaning that you should go. Okay,
ולא ליכתוב למהך, ve-lo lichtov le-me-hach, don't write a ח chet instead
of a ה, heh, make it clear that the- that the- that
the leg is separated from the roof there, דמשמע למיחך de-mash-ma le-mi-hach
as a joke. Okay, למיחך, le-mi-hach, this should be as- as a
joke, this is a פורים תורה, Purim Torah, okay, this should be
to laugh about. Okay, that's what למיחך le-mi-hach means. Okay, so you
have to be careful about how you write that. דיתנסבן De-yit-nas-van that
you should- any man that you desire, or that you should- I'm
sorry, למהך דיתנסבן, le-me-hach de-yit-nas-van, what was it? Here, רש"י Rashi now
here let's read the רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi has the basic נוסח
הגט. nusach ha-get. If you look at רש"י Rashi it's about two
lines above where the line above the הגהות הב"ח Hagahot Ha-Bach is
in the left hand column. רש"י Rashi says, זהו טופס הגט, zehu
to-fes ha-get, this is the basic language of the גט. get. פטירות
יכי ליכי, Petirus ye-chi li-chi,
I have freed you to yourself, אנת פלונית בת פלוני, ant plonit
bat ploni, you, you know, רחל בת שרה, Rachel bat Sarah, דהוית
אינתתי מן קדמת דנא, de-ha-veit inteti min kad-mat de-na, that you were
my wife prior to this, וכדו, ve-cha-du,
and with this, פטירת ושבקת ותריכת יכי, pe-ti-rat u-sh-va-kat ve-ta-ri-chat ye-chi, I
have released and divorced and whatever released you, די תהויין רשאה ושלטאה
בנפשיכי, di te-ha-ve-yan ra-sha-a u-shal-ta-a be-naf-shi-chi, that you should be permitted and
under your own control, under your- למהך ולהתנסבא לכל מאן די תיצביין,
le-me-hach u-le-hit-nas-ba le-chol man di te-tzav-yan, to go and be married to
anybody you desire, ואנש
לא ימחי בידייכי, ve-inash lo yim-chei be-ya-dai-chi,
and no man shall protest or stand in your way, מן יומא
דנן ולעלם, min yo-ma de-nan u-le-alam, from this day forward, ודן די
יהוי ליכי מינאי, ve-den di ye-ha-vei li-chi mi-nai, and this should be
to you from me, גט פטורין וספר תירוכין ואיגרת שבוקין, get pi-tu-rin
ve-se-fer ti-ru-chin ve-i-ge-ret she-vu-kin, כדת משה וישראל. ke-dat Moshe ve-Yisrael. Of course
notice what words it didn't have there.
Anybody knows what words it didn't have? הרי את מותרת לכל אדם.
Which is also there, but for some reason רש"י Rashi did not
include it. Anyway, notice
also
but
it didn't have... No, they write it in they write it in
this way. This is exactly the נוסח nusach that's used.
I mean
look, I understand, look how crazy the גמרא'ס Gemara's going about worrying
about every letter here.
Yeah. Any significance to the fact that she's referred to by as
her mother's daughter rather than her father's?
No, בת פלוני, bas ploni, not בת
פלונית. bas plonis. פלונית בת פלוני.
plonis bas
ploni.
She's her father's daughter, right, it does still still the patriarchy. Wait,
did I say רחל בת שרה?
Rachel
bas Sarah?
Oh I did, oh that was my mistake. So sorry, not רחל
בת שרה. Rachel bas Sarah. Okay. רחל בת
לבן Rachel bas Lavan there. Okay so fine, okay,
that was my mistake. Okay so back to גמרא, Gemara okay? So
ולו ליכתוב v'lo lichtov okay, so כי okay, דיהויין, d'yihavyan,
so that is that you should be permitted, דיצביאן d'yitzyavan any man
that you desire, תלתא תלתא יודין. tlosa tlosa yudin. דיהויין d'yihavyan
you see after the ו vav between the נ nun and after
the ב and between the נ, nun, there's three יודין. yudin. דמשמע
דהויין ותיהויין d'mashma d'havayan v'tihavyan
that you should be and you should desire. Now what else could
it mean? So רש״י Rashi says if you just wrote it with
two יודין, yudin, it should be תהויין tehavayan like
that women should be able to, דיהויין d'yihavyan that you should marry
two men that you know women desire, but to make it personal
that you should be able to, that you should desire, it has
to be דיהויין דיצביאן. d'yihavyan d'yitzyavan.
Okay somehow with only two would mean like that just that any
man that should be desired, that anybody would desire.
And in our משנה Mishnah.
they have it with just... I understand. Now תוספות Tosafot actually says
you need five יודין. yudin. You need the three יודין yudin at
the end and you need the יוד yud between you know and
you need the two יודין yudin there one before the ת taf
and one after the ת. taf. We'll look at תוספות Tosafot in
a minute. Okay, okay. ולוכיה לוו v'lochyei l'vav דתירוכין d'teiruchin
and you should make the ו vav of תירוכין teiruchin long. It's
sort of like מגילת אסתר, Megillas Esther, right? What is it? The
ו vav of ויזתא Vaizasa here? ולוו דשיבוקין. v'vav d'shivukin. דמשמע תירוכין
ושיבוקין d'mashma teiruchin v'shivukin
that it should mean that you should be divorced and released as
opposed to what? So again רש״י Rashi says if it did not
have the long ו vav and it was read as a יוד
yud and it was read as
איגרת תיריכין ושביקין igueres teirichin v'shivikin it would be, what does רש״י
Rashi say that that would mean? Hold on, רש״י Rashi says
one
minute, רש״י Rashi says די לא
מחזי כיוד משמע ספר תירוכין גרושות di lo mechzei k'yud mashma sefer
teiruchin gerushos
oh
a book of divorcees, a book of released women. So תירוכין teiruchin
means of divorce, שיבוקין shivukin of release, but שיביקין shivikin means women
who have been divorced, women who have been released. Okay so therefore
you have to have the ו vav and not a יוד. yud.
ולוכיה לוו דכדו v'lochyei l'vav d'chado through this,
דמשמע d'mashma actually here דמשמע d'mashma does not mean so it should
mean, it means so it shouldn't mean וכדי u'chadi for naught, okay
with that if it looked like a יוד yud it would mean
וכדי u'chadi for naught, okay? So דמשמע d'mashma here means because if
you didn't do that it would sound like it meant כדי kadi
like before it says if you didn't do that it would sound
like it meant a book of
divorcees or women who are released. It has to be תירוכין teiruchin
divorce, release, and here without the long ו vav of כדו kado
it would have sounded like it meant כדי kadi for nothing, for
naught, which is not the word that we're going for here. Okay,
okay. Where are we?
Okay. ולו ליכתוב לאינסבא v'lo lichtov l'itnasva okay,
with an א alef that you should go marry, דמשמע d'mashma because
then it would sound like it would say לא ינסבא lo yitnasva
you should not marry, אלא להינסבא ela l'hinasva that you should be
enabled to be married. Okay, so all these types of things that
it should not be misread. איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, so now they
raise a question. בעינן ודין או לא בעינן ודין? ba'inan v'dein o
lo ba'inan v'dein? Now bottom line after all that wonder you know
hyper-focus on every little letter, we want to get back to the
basic issue of the משנה. Mishnah Do you need do we פסקן
pasken like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. do you need to explicitly say
this should be a bill of divorce or not? Do you need
that whole line? תא שמע, come and hear, דאקין רבא בגיטי. d'akin
Rava b'guitti. רבא Rava made a establishment about the language of a
גט. get איך פלניא בר פלניא, eich planya bar planya, how I
ראובן בן שמעון, Reuven ben Shimon, פטר ותריך ית פלניתא איתתי pattar
v'tarich yat plonisa ittati דהוות איתתי מן קדמת דנא. d'havas ittati min
kadmat dena. I have divorced and released so-and-so my wife who has
been my wife until this point, מן יומא דנן ולעלם, min yoma
den u'l'alam, from this day forward. ואילו ודין לא קאמר, v'ilu v'dein
lo ka'amar, but when רבא Rava was establishing the נוסח nusach for
the גט get. he did not
say ודין, v'dein, and this should be, that it was not didn't
say referential.
Sounds like he did not פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
so you see he doesn't seem to פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda So the גמרא Gemara says ולטעמיך כולהו מי קאמר? u'l'ta'ameicha
kulhu mi ka'amar? One minute the גמרא Gemara. says, that נוסח nusach
was not the whole נוסח הגט. nusach ha'get. That was one particular
line that he was adding in. So the fact you can't infer
something from the fact that he didn't say ודין. v'dein. He also
didn't say הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. He didn't say a lot
of the lines. He was only talking about one particular piece that
he was adding in. אלא בעינן, ela ba'inan, so the other parts
we need but he didn't mention it. הכי נמי בעינן. hachi nami
ba'inan. and so maybe we need ודין vedein and he didn't mention
it. So with the hyperfocus on everything being like so explicit, there's
not much of a חידוש chiddush that the גמרא's Gemara, conclusion is,
you know, that you have to—thank you so much—that you have to
basically explicitly, you know, פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and
do the ודין דהוי ליכי. vedein dehavei likhi. If you don't, is
it פסול בדיעבד? pasul bedi'avad? That maybe is not so clear. But
certainly, like if you don't have all these extra יודין, yudin, is
that פסול בדיעבד? pasul bedi'avad? So that's a question, but certainly as
a לכתחילה lechatchila we want to be as explicit and as clear
as possible. Now, one minute, let's just finish this up and then
we'll talk about תוספות Tosafot for a minute. The text says מיומא
דנן—now Miyoma denan let's talk about what רבא Rava did insist on.
Okay, so the things that רבא Rava added was that it has
to say 'from this day forward', מיומא דנן, Miyoma denan, לאפוקי מדרבי
יוסי. la'fokei miderabbi Yosei. So why are you saying 'from this day'?
Because we're not going to rely on רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei, דאמר
זמנו של שטר מוכיח עליו. de'amar zmano shel shtar mokhi'ach alav. You
might remember רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says that since the גט get
is dated, it's implicit that it takes effect as of today, and
you don't need to say מעכשיו me'achshav and any condition is understood
to be retroactive. So רבא Rava did not want to rely on
that. And רבא Rava said you should state explicitly as of today.
Okay, ולעלם—and ule'olam forever. Why did he have to say that? This
day forward, לאפוקי מדבעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן, la'fokei mideba'ei minei Rava
meRav Nachman, in order to—to remove any issues like the question רבא
Rava asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, דאמר היום את אשתי ולמחר את
אשתי. de'amar hayom at ishti ulemachar at ishti. Remember the question? Can
you say 'today you're divorced from me and tomorrow not'? So just
so somebody should not create problems and go 'oh, maybe you're only
divorced for the day', so of course even though we פסקן pasken
in the end that doesn't work or whatever, that even if it's
just for the day, it's for forever, but רבא Rava wanted to
say explicitly 'from this day forward'. Okay, and that's the end of
רבא's Rava תקנה. takana. Now, תוספות Tosafot by the way, look at
one or two interesting תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says, okay... wait
a minute...
תוספות Tosafot by the way quotes the מגילה, Megilla, כל דברי האגרת
הזאת. kol divrei ha'igeret hazot. Okay...
and then תוספות Tosafot says like this, one minute... דתהויין דתצטביין, detihavyan
detitztabyan, you
see that תוספות, Tosafot, בתלתא יודין. bitlata yudin. ואמר ר"י שראה בתיקון
גיטין קדמונין—and ve'amar Ri she-ra be-tikun gittin kadmonin he saw in the,
you know, in like early גיטין, gittin, but this also might mean
like in the—in a נוסח nusach for early גיטין, gittin, an early
נוסח nusach that חמישה יודין צריכין—he chamisha yudin tzerikhin needs five יודין.
yudin. תלתא יודין ביחד בסוף דתהויין, tlata yudin beyachad besof detihavyan, and
it shouldn't be דתהויין, detihavyan, that 'women' should be, but 'you' should
be.
ואחר ד' ואחר ט' דתהויין דתצטביאן. ve'achar dalet ve'achar tet detihavyan detitztabyan.
וכן כתוב בתיקון שטרו של רב יוסף טוב עלם, vekhen katuv betikun
shtaro shel Rav Yosef Tov Elem, who was an early בעל תוספות.
Ba'al Tosafot. ודי דתהויין שתי תיבות. vedi detihavyan shtei teivot. ודי במקום
אשר, vedi bimkom asher, that you should be. Okay, then he goes
on. Okay, and now look at the next תוספות, Tosafot, וארכי לו"ו,
ve'arkhei levav, פשיטא לא צריך להאריך. peshita lo tzarikh leha'arikh. It doesn't
literally mean that the ו"ו vav has to be longer than the
other letters, like צריך באז ישיר tzarikh be-Az Yashir or something. אלא
לומר שלא יעשה קצרה, ella lomar shelo ye'aseh ketzara, you should be
careful that it shouldn't be short, שתראה יו"ד, she-tera'eh yud, that it
shouldn't look like a יו"ד. yud. Then it wouldn't be, you know,
then it wouldn't be—what was that word
for—which was—תירוכין, terukhin, it shouldn't be תריכין, terikhin, divorced women, it should
be of divorce.
וכן רגל ה"א דמהך להרחיק מן הגג, vekhen regel hei demeihakh leharkhik
min hagag, שמא צריך להרחיק, shema tzarikh leharkhik, אלא... שמא אין צריך
להרחיק, shema ein tzarikh leharkhik, you don't have to make it very,
you know, distant from the roof for the ה"א, hei, but it
means is אלא שלא יחבר בגגה, ella shelo yekhaber begagah, don't make
it look like a חי"ת. chet. Okay, it's not like you have
to make it extra so far away from the top of the
roof of the ה"א. hei. ושמא צריך להאריך הו"ו ולהרחיק רגל ה"א.
v'shema tzarikh leha'arikh havav uleharkhik regel hei. No, maybe you have to
do it extra extra, you know,
emphasis and להרחיק. uleharkhik. ומיבדי דאין הגט פסול אם לא האריך. umivadai
de'ein haget pasul im lo he'erikh. וכן הה"א דמהך אם לא הרחיק
יותר מדי. vekhen hahei demeihakh im lo hirchik yoter midai. Okay, if
you didn't make it
an extraly pronounced difference, it's okay. But on the other hand, what
if it actually does look like a יו"ד? yud? What if it
actually does look like a חי"ת? chet? So that he's going to
tell you.
ומעשה בגט שלא היה ניכר היטב בין ו"ו ליו"ד, uma'aseh beget shelo
haya nikar heitev bein vav leyud, there was actually a גט get,
where it wasn't so clear whether it was a ו"ו vav or
a יו"ד, yud, שבא לפני רבי אליהו והביא תינוק דלא חכים ולא
טיפש, sheba lifnei Rabbi Eliyahu veheivi tinok dela chakim vela tipeish, he
brought a young kid who was not too smart and not too
stupid, just right, לקרות אותו התיבה likrot oto hateiva to read it.
כאמר במנחות גבי תפילין, ke'amar beMenachot gabei tefillin, אייתיתי תינוק דלא חכים
ולא טיפש, aititi tinok dela chakim vela tipeish, וקרא ויהרה כשר אי
לא ויהרה והוא פסול. vekarei veyeihareh kasher i lo veyeihareh vehu pasul.
I don't know what the פסוק pasuk was, ויהרג veyeihareg and does
he read ויהרג veyeihareg or ויהריג veyeihareig with two יודין, yudin, ויהרוג,
veyeiharog, I don't know, anyway. So anyway, so תוספות Tosafot says...
does the ו"ו vav look like a יו"ד?
yud? So תוספות Tosafot says... yeah, so the same way for ספרי
תורה. sifrei Torah. So you have to go ahead and you would
get a תינוק tinok to go ahead and determine what the letter
looked like. So very interesting right about how this really does play
out and raises can raise questions by גיטין. gittin. Is this all
just לכתחילה? lechatchila? How much of this is בדיעבד bedi'avad and so
on? You might have a יו"ד yud question?
Yeah, you know, רש"י Rashi and
you know, read beforehand the רי"ף, Rif, the רמב"ם, Rambam, you know,
quoted the whole—this whole long text of the גט. get גמרא Gemara
only had like a few lines. And were they all in agreement
about the rest of it?
I don't know, I mean clearly there was a מסורה, mesora, that's
why תוספות Tosafot refers to
תיקון גיטין.
tikun gittin. I'm just wondering when we finally got a נוסח Nusach
of.
I don't know, I'm sure people have an answer to that. Okay,
let's take a look top of ט"ו עמוד א'. Tet-Vav Amud Aleph.
גופו של גט שחרור הרי את בת חורין הרי את לעצמך. Gufo
shel Get shichrur harei at bat chorin harei at le'atzmech. אתקין רב
יהודה בשטר זביני, Atkin Rav Yehuda bish'tar zvini, so Rav Yehuda established
by a bill of sale of a slave דעבדי, de'avdi, עבדא דנן
avda denan מוצדק לעבדו mustak le'avdo ופטיר ואטיר מן חרורי. ufatir ve'atir
min charuri. That I'm selling my slave, okay, and it is, it's
like totally
unquestioned, like just you know, that he is being sold as a
slave, meaning there's no challenge to his status as a slave. ופטיר
ואטיר מן חרורי, Ufatir ve'atir min charuri, and he is exempt and
free from any freedom, meaning there's no way that I freed him
and yeah, exempt from freedom. No way that he's been freed that
you know, you the purchaser are not aware of. ומן עלולי ומן
ערורי Umin iluli umin iruri and from any types of challenges, any
you know, claims that he was sold to somebody else, or you
know, maybe that the government has rights to him, that he's being
seized by for back payment of taxes. מן עלולי ומן ערורי מלכא
ומלכתא, Min iluli umin iruri malka umalketa, the king and the queen.
ורשום דאיניש לא אית ליה עלוי, Vershum de'inish lo it lei alavi,
and nobody has any like any right, any you know,
what's the word, like a stamp on him, meaning that he doesn't
belong to anybody else.
Okay, exactly like pressed into anyone else's service.
Exactly. That's a nice way of saying it, right? Okay. ומנוקה מכל
מין Umenuke micol min and any מום mum and he doesn't have
any blemish that is not obvious.
Like let's say a missing eye. Right, right.
So if you afterwards buy him and find out that hey, somebody
else had him you know, you know, had him he was being
held as you know, somebody had a lien on him or the
king actually had rights to him or whatever, then you can come
back to me for reimbursement because I'm promising you that there are
none of those problems. Okay. ומן שחין, Umin shechin, and it's not,
he doesn't even have some types of a you know, boils or
whatever, דנפיק עד תרתין שנין, denafik ad tartin shanin, that would come
out for two years. Apparently, boils can go in remission for up
to two years. So if anywhere within two years some boils come
out, or whatever, then I'm taking responsibility for that.
חדתא ועתיקא, Chadta ve'atika, new or old. Boils. מאי אסותיה? Mai asutei?
Now that we're talking about, we just want to remind you about
how much we dealt with how you heal things during גיטין. Gittin.
Okay, all these different medical remedies. What do you do for boils?
אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: גילברא ומרתכא וכבריתא gilbera umartacha vechavrita וחלא דחמרא
ומשחא דזיתא. vechala dechamra umishcha dezaita. So what are all these things?
So רש"י Rashi says גילברא gilbera is Rashi says ginger. Okay. ומרתכא
Umartacha is Rashi says some type of a silver dross. Is it
litharge? Yeah, I guess. וכבריתא Vechavrita Rashi says is, oh, sulfur. Okay.
And wine vinegar and olive oil ונטפי חיוורא, venatfi chivra, and some
type of a white I don't know dripping. I don't know what
נטפי natfi is. What does it say there? Naptha. Naptha. Okay. ושיפי
ליה בגדפא דאווזא, Veshayifi lei begadpa de'avza, and you spread it on
with a with a feather of a goose. Okay.
And there you go.
That'll solve your boils. Nice one little like you know cure. Exactly.
We've had enough cures. Okay, next משנה. Mishnah Yes. If we're using
רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda version, then is that
also how we
follow his
decision between the debate with the
rabbis in the earlier question? Well this רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is
not the רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, of the משנה.
Mishnah, This is the רב יהודה Rav Yehuda of the אמורא. Amora.
But it sounded from the previous גמרא Gemara anyway that we were
following רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and that is
the standard נוסח nusach I guess. Okay, but this is such a
disturbing few lines about about selling a slave. Welcome to the fact
that they really had slaves. Right, yep. Okay, yeah we talk about
it as this
halachic construct and we can have interesting discussions about
קנין גוף kinyan guf and קנין איסור kinyan issur and all these
types of things but yeah they owned slaves right like everybody else
in the ancient world. If it develops 18 months after the sale
and goes off? Well I don't know what this is but whatever.
I can't tell you what the exact שחין shechin problem was. Let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishnah שלשה גיטין פסולים ואם נישאת
הולד כשר. Shelosha gittin pesulim ve'im nisset havlad kasher. There are three
invalid גיטין gittin that nevertheless the child דיעבד di'eved will be כשר.
kasher. It's not a ולד ממזר. vlad mamzer. The גמרא's Gemara going
to discuss either this משנה Mishnah is going like not like רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir who always says הולד ממזר havlad mamzer even for
rabbinic problems or it is going like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir but
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is willing to concede that in these cases
they were not so strict. Even though ironically some of these cases
seem a lot more problematic than some of the problems of רבי
מאיר. Rebbi Meir. You remember like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir even had
a problem of even if you dated it to the wrong government,
right? To some other foreign government or to בנין בית המקדש binyan
beit hamikdash or something. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir seemed to be
pretty exacting even tiny problems. Here however the child will not be
a ממזר mamzer if even though this is rabbinically invalid. What are
they? Does this משנה Mishnah. separate from? Well we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara Does she have to separate or not? כתב
בכתב ידו ואין עליו עדים. Katav bichtav yado ve'ein alav edim. That
it's not signed but it's the person's handwriting. Now, whose position is
this? Is this רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says you don't need
it to be
signed, it's עדי מסירה כרתי? edei mesira kartei? That would be the
easiest thing
to say, except at the end of the משנה, Mishnah the end
of the משנה Mishnah introduces רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So it sounds
like the beginning of the משנה Mishnah is not רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. So there are two possibilities here. Either it's רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir that says עדי חתימה כרתי edei chasima kartei it has to
be signed, but the point is signed means it has to testify
about itself. Well, if it's your own handwriting, it's sort of like
הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hoda’as ba’al din k’me’ah eidim dami.
If it's the person's own handwriting, then you don't need external testimony.
The handwriting testifies as the person saying it himself. It creates its
own sense of testimony. But you don't see in there... No, no,
it's just in his handwriting. When I sign a check, I don't
need witnesses. That's my signature, right? When I sign a document... Now,
sometimes we get that I sign a document, we got to get
it validated. Right, that's sort of like, you know, what's it called?
Notarized. But you know what? If you have witnesses signing it, you
also get to get their signatures validated.
Fundamentally, my own signature is my own testimony. Now, it's not objective...
Right, that's true. It is writing. You're right. Writing in my handwriting.
It's true, it's not signing. Okay, but anyway, but that's... so it
could be that that works for עדות eidus for רבי מאיר. Rebbi
Meir. That's at least what תוספות Tosafos says. רש״י Rashi has even
a third possibility, that it's not רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, it's not
רבי יהודה, it does not work as עדות, eidus, but you don't
need עדי מסירה כרתי. edei mesira kartei. You don't need עדות eidus
at all in a גט. get. All you need is a גט
get, to be expressing... the husband... if it's written by a third
party, it's no good. But if it's written by the husband and
it's the husband's own expression that he is divorcing his wife, maybe
that's good without עדות. eidus. רש״י Rashi puts that out as the
possibility, which is shocking. Thank you for waiting till like the last
two דפים dappim
of the מסכת maseches to
say maybe you don't need עדות eidus as a part of a
גט. get, Like, that's been like the most stable assumption we've had.
But the more easy assumption is what תוספות Tosafos said, that your
own handwriting essentially constitutes עדות. eidus. You're testifying about yourself. Okay, so
anyway, that's handwriting, ואין עליו עדים. ve’ein alav eidim. יש עליו עדים
ואין בו זמן yeish alav eidim ve’ein bo zman, there's no date.
Because dating was very important, the whole discussion we had earlier to
know exactly when it was effective. Okay, יש בו זמן ואין בו
אלא עד אחד, yeish bo zman ve’ein bo ela eid echad. or
there is a זמן, zman, but there's only one witness. Now, why
is one witness good? So whereas here the גמרא, Gemara there are
two opinions. Either it's your handwriting plus one witness, so it's really
then just a variation of the first case. Right? Whether it's your
handwriting alone or your handwriting with one witness... You don't need the
second case. Well, no, because each one is telling you... One is
telling you that even if it's just your handwriting, it's still פסול...
pasul... כשר בדיעבד. kasher bedieved. And the other is saying even if
it's your handwriting plus one witness, it's still פסול לכתחילה. pasul l’chatchila.
Okay, but one way of understanding it is that they're just variations
of the handwriting. But the other case is, no, it's not your
handwriting. The סופר's sofer writing of the גט get is implicitly one
עד, eid, the fact that the סופר sofer wrote the גט, get
and the עד eid is the second עד. eid. Okay, and that
would be the way in which you would have עדות. eidus. Now,
by the way, I do want to say something about the way
that this is phrased, because this is phrased in a great way
for oral memory. Right? It could have said, you know what the
שלושה גיטין פסולים shlosha gittin psulim are? כתב ידו, ksav yado, אין
בו זמן, ein bo zman, יש בו עד אחד. yeish bo eid
echad. Those are essentially the שלושה גיטין פסולים. shlosha gittin psulim. But
the way it says it lets you move from one to the
next, right? כתב כתב ידו ואין עליו עדים, kasav ksav yado ve’ein
alav eidim, יש עליו עדים yeish alav eidim ואין בו זמן, ve’ein
bo zman יש בו זמן yeish bo zman ואין בו אלא עד
אחד. ve’ein bo ela eid echad, Right? It's completely, you know, one
phrase brings you to the next phrase. And it would be the
opposite of the other. You have ואין עליו ve’ein alav then יש
עליו. yeish alav. "אין" ein becomes "יש". yeish.
Then something else is "אין" and then "יש".
yeish. Exactly, exactly. Okay, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר... omer... now, הרי
אלו שלושה גיטין פסולים harei elu shlosha gittin psulim these are invalid
rabbinically. ואם נישאת הולד כשר ve’im niseis havalad kasher בדיעבד bedieved the
child will be כשר, kasher, not be a ממזר. mamzer. רבי אליעזר
אומר אף על פי שאין עליו עדים אלא שנתנו לו בפני עדים
Rabbi Eliezer omer af al pi she’ein alav eidim ela shenasno lo
bifnei eidim even if a גט get has no witnesses, as long
as it's given before witnesses, classic position of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
עדי מסירה כרתי. edei mesira kartei. Okay, even if it's written in
not your handwriting, the handwriting of the סופר, sofer, etc., כשר. kasher.
וגובה מנכסים משועבדים vegoveh minechasim meshubadim it's totally כשר לכתחילה. kasher l’chatchila.
You can even use it to collect from encumbered property, meaning if
it's a document not of divorce but if it's a loan document.
Still don't let her get married though, like, you know, so... No,
well you might need to produce the witnesses. But if you do
produce the witnesses, that's what the תיקון עולם tikkun olam is. שאין
עדים חותמים על הגט אלא מפני תיקון עולם. she’ein eidim chosmin al
haget ela mipnei tikkun olam. You'd rather have them sign so you
don't have to get the witnesses to show up to בית דין.
beis din. That helps the woman. But if they're not signed and
they do show up to בית דין beis din and they testify
that they was there, it's a hundred percent a גט.
get She can collect
her כתובה kesubah
from things that
have liens on them.
If it's not
a גט, get?
if it's a document of...
if it's a loan document, it creates liens even though you only
have liens with a written document. The presence of witnesses outside of
the document make it as weighty as if the witnesses were signed
in the document. To prove it, you need to produce the witnesses,
but the weight of the document is totally לכתחילה. l’chatchila. That's רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. But if you don't produce them? I understand. Okay,
exactly. ותו ליכא vesu leka now the גמרא Gemara says, are there
no other invalid? valid גטין? Gittin? היי גט ישן? Hai get yashan?
How about the old גט, get the גט get. that was written
then they slept together and then it was given afterwards and that
they didn't like because maybe the woman became pregnant before the גט
get. was given. So the גמרא Gemara says
and the date was earlier though.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם לא תצא. hatam lo tetzei.
No, no, no, that wasn't in this list because there בדיעבד bedieved
she doesn't have to get divorced. הכא תצא hacha tetzei here she
would have to get I know, here she'd have to get divorced.
So that's not clear in the משנה. Mishnah The משנה Mishnah just
says the kids are not ממזרים. mamzerim. So the גמרא Gemara says
הניחא למן דאמר הכא תצא. hani nicha leman d'amar hacha tetzei. So
the גמרא's Gemara going to say we're going to see a debate
whether in this משנה Mishnah before she's had kids, is she supposed
to get divorced if she has this גט get and she doesn't
have kids. So if you say she is supposed to get divorced,
then we understand that these are weightier than the גט ישן get
yashan case. The גט ישן get yashan she's not supposed to get
divorced. Okay, הניחא למן דאמר הכא תצא. hani nicha leman d'amar hacha
tetzei. אלא למן דאמר הכא לא תצא, ella leman d'amar hacha lo
tetzei, but if you say here after the גט get is given
even without kids she does not need to get divorced, so מאי
איכא למימר? mai ikka l'meimar? So we should include גט ישן. get
yashan. That's also same הלכה. halakha. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
התם תנשא לכתחילה. hatam tinnasei l'chatchila. There it's even less weighty. There,
not only do you not have to get divorced, if a גט
ישן get yashan was given she can לכתחילה l'chatchila get married. You're
not supposed to give it, but once you gave it, לכתחילה l'chatchila
she can get married. הכא בדיעבד. hacha bedieved. Here it's only once
she's married she doesn't have to get divorced. So we didn't include
גט ישן. get yashan. גט ישן get yashan is not as weighty
of a problem. Let's just get a little bit further. ואיכא גט
קרח. v'ikka get kerei'ach. How about the bald גט? get Remember the
גט get that had all the folds that didn't have one of
them signed? Okay, so why isn't that listed in here? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, התם הולד ממזר. hatam havlad mamzer. You might
remember there it says although that seems like a very trivial problem,
that there it
said that the kid would be a ממזר mamzer if they married
on the basis of this. הכא ולד כשר. hacha vlad kasher. Here
the kid is כשר. kasher. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, הניחא
לרבי מאיר, hani nicha l'Rabbi Meir, that's good for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir דאמר כל המשנה ממטבע שטבעו חכמים בגיטין הולד ממזר. d'amar kol
hameshanne mimatbei shetav'u chachamim begitin havlad mamzer. So he says over there
it's ממזר, mamzer, so here's the key question: could our משנה Mishnah
be רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Could רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir concede that
there are some cases that the kid won't be a ממזר mamzer
that will be
done wrong and be פסול pasul but not as completely you know
completely bad as those earlier cases. So the גמרא's Gemara saying it's
possible and you've got to admit for a moment that this is
totally bizarre. Something that has 10 folds and only 9 of them
are signed, in that case הולד ממזר. havlad mamzer. Something that is
missing a date or doesn't have עדים edim or only has one
signature, oh okay בדיעבד bedieved the kid isn't a ממזר. mamzer. It's
like the exact opposite of what you would expect. But you know
maybe that's his point, maybe his point is that the things that
are more trivial need more like reinforcing you know. But anyway, so
the גמרא's Gemara suggesting that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir could say in
that earlier משנה Mishnah הולד ממזר havlad mamzer and in this משנה
Mishnah these are less bad or they're not as consequential and the
kid won't be a ממזר. mamzer. So that would explain why they
wouldn't be in this list, why the list shouldn't be combined because
רבי maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, really has two different lists. אלא
לרבנן מאי איכא למימר? ella l'Rabbanan mai ikka l'meimar? But if it's
the רבנן, Rabbanan, if this משנה Mishnah is not רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir this משנה mishna that says the kid isn't a ממזר mamzer
is the רבנן Rabbanan that never say the kid is a ממזר,
mamzer, so why not include in this משנה mishna גט קרח? get
kerei'ach? Right you got it? So the רבנן Rabbanan never say the
kid is a ממזר. mamzer. So according to them you should have
all the cases together. If it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and there
are two lists, the lists of the cases that are פסול pasul
and the kid is a ממזר mamzer and the list of cases
that's not, we understand why he didn't combine the lists. But if
it's the רבנן, Rabbanan, there's only one list: it's פסול pasul and
בדיעבד bedieved the kid isn't a ממזר, mamzer, so combine the lists.
And the reason it's not a ממזר mamzer for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. would be why? Because it's not considered מטבע matbei somehow?
Yeah, that's what an earlier תוספות Tosafos said. It's like כל המשנה
ממטבע שטבעו חכמים kol hameshanne mimatbei shetav'u chachamim except when the חכמים
chachamim say that this is not a מטבע matbei problem and בדיעבד
bedieved it's not a problem. Anyway, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
אלא לרבנן מאי איכא למימר? ella l'Rabbanan mai ikka l'meimar? התם תצא
הכא לא תצא. hatam tetzei hacha lo tetzei. No, there's still a
difference. By the גט קרח get kerei'ach בדיעבד bedieved you have to
get divorced. Here you don't have to get divorced. So the גמרא
says one minute, הניחא למן דאמר הכא לא תצא. hani nicha leman
d'amar hacha lo tetzei. That's true if you say in this case
it's you don't have to get divorced. אלא למן דאמר הכא תצא,
ella leman d'amar hacha tetzei, the one that says you do have
to get divorced, it's only the kid who isn't a ממזר mamzer
but you have to get divorced, מאי איכא למימר? mai ikka l'meimar?
How is this different than the גט קרח? get kerei'ach? They both
have the exact same הלכה halakha according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. So
the גמרא says no, במקושר לא קאמרי. bimkushar lo ka'amre. Yeah, because
we're talking about a simple גט. get, We're not dealing with cases
of a folded גט. get. So that's why we didn't mention it.
Okay, one minute, ואיכא של מלכות? v'ikka shel malkhus? How about the
dating that it has to be dated according to the local government?
Okay, and that so why aren't those that in this list? התם
תצא הכא לא תצא. hatam tetzei hacha lo tetzei. There again, there
according to the רבנן Rabbanan at least, even if the kid isn't
a ממזר, mamzer, we would say they have to get divorced. Here
we wouldn't have to get divorced. גמרא says again, הניחא למן דאמר
הכא לא תצא. hani nicha leman d'amar hacha lo tetzei. That's true
if you say in our משנה mishna, you don't have to get
divorced. It's only you know that once married you can stay married.
אלא למן דאמר הכא תצא, ella leman d'amar hacha tetzei, but according
to the opinion that says in our משנה mishna you do have
to get divorced, it's only the kid who isn't a ממזר, mamzer,
so מאי איכא למימר? mai ikka l'meimar? Why not include the case
of the dating of the government? Same הלכה. halakha. In both cases
you have to get divorced and if not the kid is a
ממזר. mamzer. So the גמרא says we'll just skip the parentheses. גמרא
says אוקימתא כרבי מאיר. okimta k'Rabbi Meir. You're right. According to that,
we would have to say that the only way to explain why
those lists are not combined is that we're going according to
רבי מאיר. That can explain why they're separate lists. But if it's
the רבנן *Rabbanan* and the kid is never a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*,
and you also say in both those earlier cases and this case
you have to get divorced, you know, even and the only difference
is that the kid isn't a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*, but if you
got even if you got remarried you'd have to get divorced, so
the הלכות *halachot* are exactly the same. Why not combine it in
the same list? And the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't have an answer. Either
you'd have to say there you have to get divorced here you
don't have to get divorced, or you say it's according to רבי
מאיר *Rebbi Meir*, and there the ולד *vlad* is ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*
and here the ולד *vlad* isn't ממזר *mamzer*. Let's just finish going
through the cases. Okay. הכא ולד כשר kasher.
*Hacha vlad kasher*. Okay, מניינא דרישא למעוטי מאי מניינא דסיפא למעוטי מאי
*minyana de-reisha le-miutei mai, minyana de-seifa le-miutei mai*? Why did we say
here these are three גיטין gittin פסולים *gittin pesulim* and then we
said at the end these are three גיטין פסולים *gittin pesulim* like
it's coming to sort of indicate that only these three. Don't add
other things to this list. So מניינא דרישא למעוטי הני דאמרן *minyana
de-reisha le-miutei hanei de-amarn*, so the first these are the three is
to exclude the cases we just have brought and discussed which would
not be included, either because these for רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* those
other cases are ולד ממזר *vlad mamzer* these are not ולד ממזר
*vlad mamzer* or for the חכמים *Chachamim* those other cases are תצא
tetzei. *teitzei* and these are cases of not תצא tetzei? *teitzei*, she
doesn't have to get divorced. מניינא דסיפא *Minyana de-seifa* now why do
we repeat it again at the end? למעוטי הא דתניא *le-miutei ha-de-tanya*,
we turned in the ברייתא *Baraita*, המביא גט get, ממדינת הים ונתנו
לה ולא אמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם *hameivi get mi-medinat ha-yam venatanu
lah velo amar bifanay nechtav uvifanay nechtam*, remember בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם
*bifanay nechtav uvifanay nechtam*, we couldn't end the מסכת *masechet* without getting
back to that first idea. Okay, if you gave it without saying
it, יצא והולד ממזר *yeitzei vehavlad mamzer* דברי רבי מאיר *divrei Rebbi
Meir*. Once again רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*, okay, kid is a ממזר
*mamzer*. וחכמים אומרים אין הולד ממזר כיצד יעשה יטלנו הימנה ויחזור ויתננו
לה בפני שנים ויאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם *ve-Chachamim omrim ein havlad
mamzer keitzad yaaseh yitlenu mimenah veyachzor veyitnenu lah bifnai shnayim veyomar bifanay
nechtav uvifanay nechtam*. No, just take it and re-give it. So what
are we doing? Why are we excluding that? Why is that a
separate case? It's the same point. If it's רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
saying other cases are ולד ממזר *vlad mamzer*, this isn't ולד ממזר
*vlad mamzer*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfot* רש״י Rashi *Rashi* is just saying,
רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says no, we want to explicitly make indicate very
subtly that there's this other case that that רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
that you would think is not so bad. You'd think it belongs
in this list. Like if I had to ask you the guy
didn't say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם *bifanay nechtav uvifanay nechtam*, would you
think the kid is a ממזר *mamzer* for רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*?
Say what are you talking about? The גט get *get* was done
perfectly, the שליח *shaliach* just didn't say בפני נכתב *bifanay nechtav*, the
שליח *shaliach* could say it again. Right? You're like a little shocked
that רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* takes his הולד ממזר *havlad mamzer* even
to this case of the בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם *bifanay nechtav uvifanay
nechtam*. So רש״י *Rashi* is saying that's why it repeats at the
end: these three בדיעבד bediavad. *bediavad* the kid isn't a ממזר *mamzer*,
but the other cases, even cases that you would think are crazy,
רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says the kid is a ממזר *mamzer*. So
not A, all the cases we said before, and not only that,
it repeats it again, only these three, to let you know that
there's even one really crazy case, just not saying בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם *bifanay nechtav uvifanay nechtam*, that even there רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
says the kid is a ממזר *mamzer*, and it's only these cases
that רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says the kid is not a
ממזר *mamzer*.
Yes. Professionally you know this is a גרושה *grusha* so she's got
remarried so you know her כתובה *ketubah* will be different. Who's writing
this כתובה *ketubah*? This seems like there's like no due diligence here.
Like you know this גט get, *get* is missing like you know
what I mean? Like did they not even see it? All right,
you're divorced let me see your your גט get *get*. Let me
just make sure you're divorced you know what I mean? Like they
could've you know this wouldn't have ever gotten to this
point if she got remarried
and then you encounter all these questions and you know תצא *teitzei*,
הולד ממזר *havlad mamzer* you know?
Who's marrying her to begin with? I don't know. What makes you
think you're doing everything through a בית דין *Beit Din*? I mean
it raises good questions but let's say the woman goes and she
shows this to the husband to the guy and the guy marries
her. Like you don't have everything I mean
no, סופר sofer's *sofer* those writing it, you know what I'm saying?
You don't know what what's a סופר sofer's *sofer* writing the כתובה
*ketubah*? Yeah. Oh I don't know. He's got to be a סופר
sofer's *sofer* that's a תלמיד חכם *Talmid Chacham*. We're gonna see in
a minute.
Like you know, anyone who's whatever it is maybe, maybe.
I mean right now somebody just told me, somebody just told me
that this whole article right now on Ynet that in Israel if
you want to avoid all of the crazy
and oppressive sort of requirements of the רבנות *Rabbanut* in terms of
being able to get married where they you know the type of
documentation they demand from you is whatever is obscene,
they say you don't you just go to this חרדי *Charedi* בית
דין *Beit Din* that has an arrangement with the Israeli Rabbinate, you
know you you know you pay them a few hundred dollars or
whatever the fee is, they basically you could basically they'll basically accept
you in forged documents. A reporter did this whole little like thing
to essentially anyway. So you know there are ways to work with
the system. Definitely there are ways. I understand, I understand. Okay, כתב
ידו ואין עליו עדים edim. *ktav yado ve-ein alav eidim*. Okay. So
let's now go through them. Handwriting with no witnesses. אמר רב כתב
ידו שנינו *Amar Rav ktav yado shaninu*. Rav says your handwriting. So
אהיי *a-hai* what are you talking about? אילימא רישא פשיטא כתב ידו
קתני *Ileima reisha peshita ktav yado katani*. Of course that was the
case, it was your handwriting. אלא מציעתא *Ella mitsiyata*, the middle case
about אין בו זמן zman, *ein bo zman*. הרי יש לה עדים
*Harei yesh lah eidim*. It says, הרי יש לה עדים *harei yesh
lah eidim*. The middle case explicitly says it has witnesses it just
doesn't have זמן *zman*. אלא סיפא seifa. *Ella seifa*, the last case,
יש בו זמן ואין בו אלא עד אחד ed echad *yesh bo
zman ve-ein bo ella eid echad*. That has only one witness. So
that's the real question, how... How could a גט get. be good
with only one witness? So he says ודווקא כתב ידך, vedavka ktav
yadcha, that last case is one witness plus your handwriting ועד. ve'ed.
אבל כתב סופר ועד, Aval ktav sofer ve'ed, if
it was the signature, if it was the סופר's sofer's handwriting, לא,
that would not be good, because the סופר's sofer's handwriting would not
count as a witness. Now why not, if your handwriting could? Well,
first of all, your handwriting is yours, הבעל דבר. haba'al davar. But
also, as we'll see, because how do you know, maybe you found
a גט get thrown out in the garbage and you just got
an עד אחד ed echad to sign it? Okay? So therefore, the
fact that it's every גט get, has some סופר's sofer handwriting. A
handwriting does not mean that I'm testifying to the veracity, right, of
this. ושמואל אמר אפילו כתב סופר ועד. Ushmuel amar afilu ktav sofer
ve'ed. No, you can even use a סופר's sofer's handwriting. That's like
one עד ed plus the one signature, that's two עדים. דהא שנינו
כתב סופר ועד כשר. Deha shaninu ktav sofer ve'ed kasher. A later
משנה mishna, is going to say a סופר's sofer's handwriting and one
witness is כשר. kasher. Now the other version is that later משנה
mishna. is not כתב סופר, ktav sofer, or that it's חתם
סופר, chatam sofer, earlier משנה, mishna it's the signature of a סופר
sofer's and an עד. ed. But if שמואל Shmuel says no, my
version of that משנה mishna is a סופר's sofer's handwriting counts as
one witness plus one signature, that's your two witnesses. Okay? So that's
for him, that's the second last case of the משנה, Mishnah which
is probably פשט pshat of the משנה. ורב דימי ורב רבותי Verav
Dimi verav rabotei back to me, מי דמי? mi dami? התם תינשא
לכתחילה. Hatam tinase lechatchila. There, that's not, we're not talking about this
case, because there it says that the woman can get married לכתחילה.
lechatchila. So why could it be more okay לכתחילה lechatchila over there?
So the way רש״י explains it is, that's why רב is saying,
buddy, you got it wrong. It's not כתב סופר, ktav sofer, it's
חתם סופר. chatam sofer.
It's the, it's the סופר's sofer's signature and another witness. And you
know my proof? Because that משנה over there says she can get
married
לכתחילה. lechatchila. והכא בדיעבד. Vehacha bediavad. Here it's פסול. pasul. So clearly
we're not talking about the סופר's sofer, handwriting. There we're talking about
the סופר's sofer's signature plus an עד ed and that's why it's
okay. הכא בדיעבד, Hacha bediavad, here it's only good בדיעבד. bediavad So
they're talking about the סופר's sofer. signature, you can't bring proof from
that. This case where it's good with one עד ed has nothing
to do with the סופר, sofer it's the husband's own handwriting. ושמואל,
Veshmuel, שמואל Shmuel would say back no,
לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא בסופר מובהק הא בסופר דלא מובהק. Ha
besofer mufhak ha besofer delo mufhak. When can you get married לכתחילה
lechatchila with a סופר's sofer handwriting plus one witness? If it's an
expert סופר. sofer, What does an expert סופר sofer have to do
with it? So רש״י and תוספות basically say because an expert סופר
sofer's would not let the גט get out of his hands unless
it was going to be signed and used, so his writing of
the גט is implicitly functioning as an עד. ed. Right, if I'm
not an expert סופר, sofer's I'll just practice writing a גט, I'll
throw it out in the garbage, somebody's going to sign it, attach
a signature to it and so on, and my writing is not
taking the onus of responsibility to understand that that is, part of
this writing is testifying to the veracity of the גט. But if
I'm a סופר מובהק, sofer mufhak, I do do that due diligence.
Okay? So with a סופר מובהק sofer mufhak plus עד אחד ed
echad, you can get married לכתחילה. lechatchila. A סופר sofer's not מובהק
mufhak plus עד אחד, ed echad. we can question whether the סופר's
sofer's handwriting counts as a type of עדות. edut. So it's פסול
לכתחילה, pasul lechatchila, but at least בדיעבד bediavad it'll be כשר. kasher,
וכן אמר רבי יוחנן, Vecheyn amar Rabbi Yochanan, and similarly said רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, כתב ידך שנינו. ktav yadcha shaninu. That no, if
it's a סופר's handwriting, it's not good. The only case that בדיעבד
b'dieved would be good would be your handwriting plus an עד אחד.
ed echad, אמר ליה רבי אלעזר, Amar lei Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar said, והרי יש עליו עדים. veharei yesh alav edim. So
one minute, it says, it says that there are witnesses. Wait, what's
going on?
רבי אלעזר סבר דאמציעתא קאי. Rabbi Elazar savar de'amtzita ka'i.
Oh, he misunderstood what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. When רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said we're talking about your handwriting, he said, what do
you mean we're talking about your handwriting? The middle case in the
משנה says there are witnesses and there's no זמן, it's not your
handwriting. אמר ליה אסיפא. Amar lei aseifa. No, no, no, I meant
the last case. The last case of עד אחד, ed echad I'm
saying it's not just עד אחד ed echad. and the סופר's handwriting,
it's your handwriting and the עד אחד. Okay? So now we are
having all these opinions that are trying to say that last case
that says one witness is not סתם stam one witness, that's a
deeply troubling case. So is it one witness, is it the סופר's
handwriting that's counting as the other witness? That's a big חידוש. chiddush.
So here רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רב and others are saying,
no, no, no, it's only with the husband's handwriting plus the one
witness is the case of the סיפא. Okay. Yes? But how is
it any different?
Because I don't understand.
Well, in the first case you had even the husband's handwriting without
any witnesses, right? It's like we said before, like you sign a
check. So it's true you don't sign it here, you just write
it. But me writing in my own handwriting is me essentially testifying
that I'm doing this.
What's the חידוש chiddush of the husband's handwriting plus a witness?
Oh, so that's what I was saying before. So it's like the
חידוש chiddush then of saying both cases is the handwriting without a
witness is still פסול, pasul, is still כשר בדיעבד, kasher bediavad, and
the handwriting with a witness is still פסול לכתחילה. pasul lechatchila. So
even though you have a range of scenarios of handwriting,
you have handwriting without a witness, handwriting with a witness. And the
point is both of them are פסול לכתחילה. pasul lechatchila. You might
have thought that with a witness it could be כשר לכתחילה. kasher
lechatchila. No, they're both פסול לכתחילה, pasul lechatchila, but both are both
כשר בדיעבד. kasher bediavad. Right, both. Yeah, or at least הולד אינו
ממזר havlad eino mamzer even if it didn't have the extra witness,
right? So it has both scenarios to tell you they both have
the same לכתחילה l'chatchila and בדיעבד b'dieved. parameters. Okay. And now the
Gemara says about this issue we referred to before about what is
the story about not the question of the kid but the question
of marriage. So the Gemara says like this. זימנין אמר רב תצא,
zimnin amar Rav tetzei, sometimes Rav said if a woman married with
any of these גיטין in the Mishnah she would have to get
divorced. זימנין אמר רב לא תצא, zimnin amar Rav lo tetzei, sometimes
he said, you know what, it's only a point about, it's not
only that the kid isn't ממזר, you don't even have to get
divorced בדיעבד. b'dieved הא כיצד? ha keitzad? But how do you reconcile
the two versions of Rav? So he actually said it depends on
the circumstances. יש לה בנים לא תצא. yesh la banim lo tetzei.
If she's already had kids then not only are the kids not
ממזרים, mamzerim, but she doesn't have to get divorced. If we forced
her to get divorced after she had kids on the base because
of this גט, people would say the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. So
if there are kids, we're not going to force a divorce. אין
לה בנים תצא. ein la banim tetzei. If she has not had
any kids yet, תצא. Okay, so מתיבי, meitivei, Rav Suta bar Tuvia:
הכלות שהיו בהן בין ספק קידושין ובין ספק גירושין הרי אלו חולצות
ולא מתייבמות. hakalot shehayu bahen bein sefek kiddushin u'vein sefek gerushin harei
elu choltzot v'lo mityabmot. All the cases of צרת ערוה, tzarat ervah,
remember, like a guy's brother is married to his daughter, so the
co-wives are exempt from יבום yibbum and חליצה chalitzah because of צרת
ערוה. tzarat ervah. Let's say the marriage to that guy's daughter was
a ספק קידושין sefek kiddushin or he was married to the guy's
daughter but then it was ספק מגורש sefek megurash from it. So
the story about the co-wives,
are the co-wives exempt or חייב chayiv in יבום? yibbum? We don't
know. If she was really married to his brother's daughter, then the
co-wives are exempt from יבום. yibbum. If he wasn't married, right, then
they're חייב. chayiv. So what do you do in those cases? You
do חליצה, chalitzah, you don't do יבום. yibbum. All right, so that's
the scenario why we're going to talk about it, but now we
spell out: what is a case that he's ספק sefek married to
his brother's daughter or ספק sefek divorced from his brother's daughter? היכי
דמי ספק קידושין? heichi dami sefek kiddushin? זרק לה קידושין ספק קרוב
לו ספק קרוב לה. zarak la kiddushin sefek karov lo sefek karov
la. You don't know if the money, the ring, got closer to
her, closer to him, did she קונה koneh the ring?
That's ספק קידושין. sefek kiddushin. מהו ספק גירושין? mahu sefek gerushin? כתב
בכתב ידו ואין עליו עדים, יש עליו עדים ואין בו זמן, יש
בו זמן ואין בו אלא עד אחד. katav b'chtav yado v'ein alav
eidim, yesh alav eidim v'ein bo zman, yesh bo zman v'ein bo
ela eid echad. הרי זה ספק. harei zeh sefek. It's really like
a ודאי vadai גירושין, gerushin, it's just a דרבנן d'rabbanan problem, but
we treat it as not really fully divorced and therefore we have
to do a
חליצה. chalitzah. הרי זה ספק גירושין. harei zeh sefek gerushin. Now, how's
that relevant to this question of תצא? Let's take a look. ואי
אמרת לא תצא, v'ei amrat lo tetzei, if you say that once
a woman has this גט בדיעבד b'dieved she doesn't have to get
divorced if she marries with it, so
רשא... rasha... אתי ליבומי. ati l'yibumei. So people will say, one minute,
this woman, this brother's, you know, this brother's daughter got this גט,
it's a גט that's בדיעבד b'dieved, כשר, kasher if she gets married
she doesn't have to get divorced, so people will think that oh
my god, so she really is divorced. So this guy might come
to do יבום yibbum with her co-wife because he'll think that, you
know, his daughter was really divorced. So that'll be terrible. So the
Gemara says: why will it be so terrible? She really is divorced,
it's only a rabbinic problem. Okay, so תתייבם בין כך ובין כך,
tityabem bein kach u'vein kach, fine, who cares? בדיעבד, b'dieved you're right,
it is only a rabbinic problem, it really is a good גט.
חששא דרבנן היא. chashasha d'rabbanan hi. Okay, so that was a strange
counter proof. But we're basically saying that בדיעבד b'dieved do we treat
this as like a really פסול pasul גט and the only thing
we'll exempt is the ממזר, or are we going to be able
to concede that בדיעבד it's כשר and even if she gets married
she doesn't have to get divorced? So let's just read one more
line on this. לוי אמר לעולם לא תצא, Levi amar l'olam lo
tetzei, if she gets married she doesn't have to get divorced. וכן
אמר רבי יוחנן לעולם לא תצא, v'chein amar Rabbi Yochanan l'olam lo
tetzei, she doesn't. וכן אמר להו רבי יוחנן לבני רב חלפתא דמנהונא
הכי אמר אבוכון לעולם לא תצא. v'chein amar lehu Rabbi Yochanan livnei
Rav Chalafta d'minhuna hachi amar avuchon l'olam lo tetzei. This is what
your father said, לעולם לא תצא. l'olam lo tetzei. If she marries
with this גט, meaning לעולם l'olam means even if she didn't have
kids, once she married with this גט she does not have to
get divorced, with or without kids. Okay, and one last line since
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was telling the sons of רב חלפתא Rav
Chalafta something their father said, here's something else their father said.
והקרצי שבעמיר, v'hakartzi she'be'amir, a certain type of a locust that hangs
out in the, in the bundles of wheat, אינה פוסלת במי חטאת.
eina poselet b'mei chatat. If it drinks from the water of a
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, it doesn't invalidate it. Okay,
מאי קרצי? mai kartzi? אמר ביידי בססא, amar bayadi bassasa, some type
of a insect or a locust or a grasshopper, דביני כפי d'veinei
kifi that's between the bundles of wheat. מתיבי רב חנינא בר רב
אידי. meitivei Rav Chanina bar Rav Idi. We say: כל העופות פסולין
במי חטאת. kol ha'ofot psulin b'mei chatat. If any bird drinks from
the water of a חטאת, chatat, it invalidates it, because we assume
the water went in the bird's mouth and then back out into
the water of the חטאת. chatat. חוץ מן היונה. chutz min hayona.
Whatever, there's a question exactly what פסול psul that is. With the
exception of a dove
מפני שמוצצת, mipnei shemotzetzet, because the dove just sucks up and it
doesn't spit back out. ואי איתא, v'im ita, if this is true,
it shouldn't have just mentioned a dove. נתני חוץ מן היונה והקרצי.
nitnei chutz min hayona v'hakartzi. Say except for the dove and this,
like, I don't know, this flying grasshopper. So Gemara says. No, לא
פסיקא ליה. lo psik lei. No, no, that grasshopper is not always
the true that it's not a problem. דגדולה לא פסלה, de'gedola lo
pasla, a big one is not a problem, it doesn't spit the
water back out, וקטנה פסלה, ve'ketana pasla, and a small one does.
ועד כמה, ve'ad kama, how big, how small is it that it's
still a problem? אמר רב ירמיא ואיתימא רב אמי, Amar Rav Yirmiya
ve'isima Rav Ami, עד כזית, ad kezayis, until the size of an
olive. Okay, completely little digression, but bottom line anyway, what we do
say is even though the משנה only says that the kid isn't
a ממזר, we say that once married you don't have to get,
that once married you don't have to get divorced even if there
are no kids.